Guide to the Personal Papers of Henry Mitchell MacCracken 1852-1910 MC 15 MC 15
New York University Archives
- Series II: Writings (Published and Unpublished)
  - Subseries D. Speeches (1857-1910)
    - Address to School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance (version 1); Address to School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance (version 2), 1904-1905 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Address to bank clerks, 1904-1905 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - [Public concern about college students], 1904-1905 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - "How Alumni May Help Their Alma Mater", 1905 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Commencement, 1905 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Opening address to School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance, 1905 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Undergraduate Colleges at New York University, 1905 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - The New Medical Laboratories, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Opening Address to Medical College, 1905 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - [Honoring Emma Willard], 1905 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Address upon death of W.A. Wheelock, President of the NYU Council, 1898-1905 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Undergraduate colleges at University Heights, 1906 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Alumni dinner [football], 1905-1906 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - New Year's address to undergraduates(reference to athletics), 1906 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Address to alumni, 1906 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - [Acceptance to tablet from Sons of the Revolution], 1906 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - [Alumni dinner honoring Dr. Stevenson], 1906 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - College opening (praise of small colleges), 1906 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - [Schwab estate], 1906 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - [Introduction of Elmer E. Brown (U.S. Commissioner of Education and later Chancellor of NYU) at Pedagogy opening), 1906 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - "The University and the Public" address (typescript), 1906-1907 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Opening College of Arts, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - [Funeral address for Thomas Swan Hubbard (father-in-law)] (newspaper), 1907 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - [Chapel Speech Re: Athletics], Nov, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Opening School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Opening Medical College (Reference to pathology), 1908 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Opening University College, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Abraham Lincoln: Reminiscences, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Racial Characteristics Among Presbyterians, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Zeta Psi address, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - First National Convention upon Athletics, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Dutch tercentenary address, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - [Honoring Dutch establishment of free schools] (typescript), 1909 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Graduates Club Address Re: NYU football policy, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Entering class of the University and Bellevue Hospital Medical College, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Athletic Association, Apr, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - "Some of the Administrative Tasks of the Last Twenty-five Years, ca.1909-1910 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Observations on employment at NYU and on behavior as chancellor, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Resume of developments at NYU, 1885-1910 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Subseries E. Speeches (undated)
    - [Carnegie Institute's aid to education], undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - "American Colleges and Universities During the Nineteenth Century" (newspaper)(Development of School of Pedagogy), undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - [Professions of law and medicine], undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Address to Emna Willard Society [teaching profession and women] versions l, 2, & 3, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Scotch-Presbyterian church anniversary, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Syracuse dinner [types of universities], undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Address to tri-city officials (Yonkers, Mt. Vernon, and New Rochelle - reference to Bronx), undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - [Legal profession in New York City], undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - "Liquor Question -- Sunday Afternoon Opening"--Civic Affairs, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - "Greene County" [Scotch-Irish]-- Biographical memoirs, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Praise of American Preachers, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Young Men's Hebrew Association - Bronx, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - "Paulsen's Theology in the German University", undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Address to Alumni Association, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Address to group to whom President Low of Columbia also to speak (Reference to progress in Washington Square Area), undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Opening address to undergraduates, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Newburgh address [history of the area's settlement], undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - [Washington's Birthday Address: Obligations of University in 20th Century, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - [Refusal to allow students to march in Presidential inaugural parade], undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Health & Honesty: Football vs. Homicide Football, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Rochester speech Re: college and professional education, 0000 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Address to alumni of Law School, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - [New York University: Spanish-American War], undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - [Sociological fieldwork for high schools], undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Society of Accountants dinner, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - [Football], undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Alumni Dinner - reference to endowments, undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Opening Day Women's Law Class, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - [Wesleyan University on policy Re: Philippines], undated (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - (Remarks Re: Ralph Waldo Emerson], undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Association of History Teachers, undated (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - [Voluntaryism for support of culture], undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - [Jersey City High School Visit], undated (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Laying cornerstone University Heights Presbyterian Church, undated (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Universities in great cities - Evolution of NYU since 1866, undated (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Alumni address - reference to Chicago World's Fair & fraternities, undated (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - "American Ideal of Government", undated (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - "The Great Window of the Auditorium" (Gould Library), undated (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - "Chancellor MacCracken's Residence" (MacCracken Hall), undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - "A Peek into the School of Pedagogy of New York University", undated (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - [Educational issues in France and England], undated (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - [Slocum ship disaster - speech at giving of medals], undated (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Address to founders of Park College - History of professional education in the U.S., undated (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - [Medical College Laboratory], undated (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - "What Shall Be Done to Improve Our Present Liquor Law", undated (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Address to alumni - role of college president, undated (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - [Dr. Loomis (NYU Council 1892-1895)tribute], undated (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - [Instruction of children], undated (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - [Medical College Consolidation], undated (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - [Fund-raising], undated (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - [Philosophy of a university], undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Address to alumni - aspirations of University, undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - "Lincoln", undated (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - [Legal profession], undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - [Plan for alumni electorate], undated (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - [Upon presenting Doctor of Divinity degree to Schaff], undated (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Society for the Prevention of Crime, undated (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - History Teachers of the Middle States, undated (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - [Sumr-er School kindergarten], undated (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Presbyterian colleges as source of graduate students for NYU, undated (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - "Science: A Force in Morals", undated (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Address to students [upon return from European trip - incomplete], undated (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - [Life insurance] - incomplete, undated (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - Letters to Newspaper Editors on Civic Matters, 1904-1909, undated (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Miscellaneous, 1906 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - History pamphlets, undated (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Clippings and Public Statenents, 1899-1907 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Subseries F. Sixty Years of School Talks, 1853-1914
    - Sixty Years of School Talks, 1853-1914; Binder of writings by Henry Mitchell MacCracken compiled by his great-grandson, Thomas G. MacCracken (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Series III. Organizations
  - St. Paul's Institute (Tarsus, Turkey): Correspondence, 1893-1898 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Presbyterian Reformed Church:, 1899-1904, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1897-1909, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Chi Alpha, 1896-1910 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - General Assembly Peace Associations and Conferences:, 1902 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - New York City Peace Society, 1907 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Saratoga National Conference on Foreign Policy, 1893 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Other Peace Conferences, 1905-1907 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1896, 1901-1907 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Andrew H. Green Memorial Association, 1903-1904 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - American Institute of Social Service, 1903-1904 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Other Associations, 1898-1907 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Series IV. Finances and Real Estate
  - Ohio: Correspondence, 1895-1899 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Ohio: Correspondence, 1900-1902 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Ohio: MacCracken, George W., 1894-1908 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Ohio: Stewart, D.M., 1895-1896 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Ohio: Ady, A.C.; Taylor, Taylor & Taylor, 1891-1900 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Ohio: Baird, W.C., 1898-1899 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Ohio: Blom, John, 1896-1900 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Ohio: Heitt, Irving B.; J.A. Granger, 1894-1901 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Ohio: Douglass, George, 1892-1899 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Ohio: Edwards, Mrs. M. E., 1896 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Ohio: Fish Stone Company, 1895-1902 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Ohio: Powell, W. G., 1896-1898 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Ohio: Wells, James M., 1897-1898 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Ohio: Insurance, 1894-1902 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Ohio: Family Farm, Correspondence, 1890-1902 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Ohio Bills, 1894-1908 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Vermont: Correspondence and Documents, 1894, 1897-1903 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - New York: Correspondence and Documents, 18961902 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Printed Material, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Ohio Tool Company, 1891-1895, 1901-1902 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Loans/Payable, 1909 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Bills, 1896-1906 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and Papers, Miscellaneous, 1897-1909 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Checks and Checkbook, 1889-1902 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Deposits and Savings Book (Second National Savings Bank), 1894-1902 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Account Book showing inventory of estate of G. G. [George Gere MacCracken]and other data on investments, payment, etc., ca.1881-1890 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- V. Diaries, Account Books, and Notebooks
  - MacCracken, Henry Mitchell: Diary, 1890 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - MacCracken, Henry Mitchell: Diary, 1898 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - MacCracken, Henry Mitchell: Marriage Certificate Book, ca.1890 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - MacCracken, Henry Mitchell: Bank of Pittsburgh Account Book, 1881-1882 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - MacCracken, Henry Mitchell: "Register of Property" Notebook, 1899 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - MacCracken, George Gere: "M.H. Lyons Institute" Report Book, 1888-1890 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - MacCracken, Catherine Hubbard: Grocery Acount Book with inserts, 1896, 1899 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - MacCracken, Henry Noble: Account Book, 1885-1890 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- VI. Artifacts
  - Engraving plate portraying John H. MacCracken, 1899 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Men's snakeskin folder purse, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
- VII. Testimonial and Retirement
  - Testimonial, New Jersey Alumni (clipping), 1909 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Retirement: Newspaper coverage, 1910 (Box 10, Folder 12)